Taren Sanders

ACADEMIC RESEARCHER & DATA SCIENTIST

Institute for Positive Psychology and Education, Australian Catholic University

□ 0412 278 640 | ☑ Taren.Sanders@acu.edu.au | ⊙ 0000-0002-4504-6008 | ⊙ tarensanders | У tarensanders

Education

Doctor of Philosophy

WESTERN SYDNEY UNIVERSITY 2016

 Thesis: Investigating associations between neighbourhood green space and weight status: A longitudinal study of Australian children aged 4 to 13 years old.

Master of Data Science (Applied)

Adelaide University 2022

Bachelor of Health Science (Honours; First Class)

WESTERN SYDNEY UNIVERSITY 2012

· Thesis: Measuring adolescent boys' physical activity: Bout length and the influence of accelerometer epoch length.

Bachelor of Health Science (PDHPE)

WESTERN SYDNEY UNIVERSITY 2011

Employment History _____

Program Leader

INSTITUTE FOR POSITIVE PSYCHOLOGY AND EDUCATION, AUSTRALIAN CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY

2021-Current

- · Drive the strategic direction and focus of the research program
- Support academic and professional staff, as well as higher-degree students, within the program
- · Provide input as a member of the Institute Executive Management Committee on Institute priorities, and advocate for my research program
- · Developed and implemented new project management processes, including making agile management strategies standard practice.

Deputy Program Leader

INSTITUTE FOR POSITIVE PSYCHOLOGY AND EDUCATION, AUSTRALIAN CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY

2017-202

• Supported Program Leader to manage the research program

Research Fellow

Institute for Positive Psychology and Education, Australian Catholic University

2016-Current

- · Conduct original, high-impact, and translational research in the areas of health, education, and psychology.
- Oversee the development, evaluation, and management of multiple large-scale school-based research projects (e.g., iPLAY; 180 schools).
- · Conduct analyses of primary and secondary data, and provided statistical support to colleagues including statistics workshops.
- · Work with industry partners (NSW Department of Education, NSW Health, Sport Australia) to provide project updates and seek input.
- Author academic and non-academic outputs, including journal articles, grant applications, stakeholder reports, and data visualisations.
- · Mentor doctoral and honours students, including reviewing and evaluating their analyses and writing.

Research Summary _____

Publications	Citations	h-Index	Mean CNCI	Mean Impact	Funding
36	1492	21	1.8	Factor 7.4	> \$1 million

Technical Skills _____

Programming Languages

R, Python, Stata, Julia

Software Development

R PACKAGES (INCLUDING CRAN SUBMISSION), PYTHON PACKAGES

Statistical Methods

MACHINE LEARNING, MULTILEVEL MODELLING, INTERVENTION EVALUATION, META-ANALYSES

Research Methods

STUDY DESIGN, INTERVENTION DEVELOPMENT, ETHICS AND RECRUITMENT

Selected Publications

For a full list of publications see my full CV (bit.ly/TarenSanders).

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Lubans, D. R., **Sanders, T.**, Noetel, M., Parker, P., McKay, H., Morgan, P., Salmon, J., Kirwan, M., Bennie, A., Peralta, L., Cinelli, R., Moodie, M., Hartwig, T., Boyer, J., Kennedy, S. G., Plotnikoff, R. C., Hansen, V., Vasconcellos, D., Lee, J., ... Lonsdale, C. (2022). Scale-up of the Internet-based Professional Learning to help teachers promote Activity in Youth (iPLAY) intervention: A hybrid type 3 implementation-effectiveness trial. *International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity*, 19(1), 141. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12966-022-01371-4

Antczak, D., Lonsdale, C., del Pozo Cruz, B., Parker, P., & **Sanders, T.** (2021). Reliability of GENEActiv accelerometers to estimate sleep, physical activity, and sedentary time in children. *International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity*, 18(1), 73. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12966-021-01143-6 | Citations: 5; JIF: 8.9; CNCI: 1.1

Noetel, M., Griffith, S., Delaney, O., Harris, N. R., **Sanders, T.**, Parker, P., del Pozo Cruz, B., & Lonsdale, C. (2021). Multimedia Design for Learning: An Overview of Reviews With Meta-Meta-Analysis. *Review of Educational Research*. https://doi.org/10.3102/00346543211052329 | Citations: 3; JIF: 13.6; CNCI: 0.6

Lee, J., **Sanders, T.**, Antczak, D., Parker, R., Noetel, M., Parker, P., & Lonsdale, C. (2021). Influences on User Engagement in Online Professional Learning: A Narrative Synthesis and Meta-Analysis. *Review of Educational Research*, 91(4), 518–576. https://doi.org/10.3102/0034654321997918 | Citations: 5; JIF: 13.6; CNCI: 2.1

Hartwig, T. B., **Sanders, T.**, Vasconcellos, D., Noetel, M., Parker, P. D., Lubans, D. R., Andrade, S., Ávila-García, M., Bartholomew, J., Belton, S., Brooks, N. E., Bugge, A., Cavero-Redondo, I., Christiansen, L. B., Cohen, K., Coppinger, T., Dyrstad, S., Errisuriz, V., Fairclough, S., ... del Pozo Cruz, B. (2021). School-based interventions modestly increase physical activity and cardiorespiratory fitness but are least effective for youth who need them most: An individual participant pooled analysis of 20 controlled trials. *British Journal of Sports Medicine*, *55*(13), 721–729. https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2020-102740 | Citations: 21; JIF: 18.5; CNCI: 3.6

Lonsdale, C., **Sanders, T.**, Parker, P., Noetel, M., Hartwig, T., Vasconcellos, D., Lee, J., Antczak, D., Kirwan, M., Morgan, P., Salmon, J., Moodie, M., McKay, H., Bennie, A., Plotnikoff, R. C., Cinelli, R., Greene, D., Peralta, L., Cliff, D., ... Lubans, D. R. (2021). Effect of a Scalable School-Based Intervention on Cardiorespiratory Fitness in Children: A Cluster Randomized Clinical Trial. *JAMA Pediatrics*, 175(7), 680. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics. 2021.0417 | Citations: 11; JIF: 26.8; CNCI: 3.6

Noetel, M., Griffith, S., Delaney, O., **Sanders, T.**, Parker, P., del Pozo Cruz, B., & Lonsdale, C. (2021). Video Improves Learning in Higher Education: A Systematic Review. *Review of Educational Research*, 91(2), 204–236. https://doi.org/10.3102/0034654321990713 | Citations: 25; JIF: 13.6; CNCI: 4.9

Antczak, D., Lonsdale, C., Lee, J., Hilland, T., Duncan, M. J., del Pozo Cruz, B., Hulteen, R. M., Parker, P. D., & **Sanders, T.** (2020). Physical activity and sleep are inconsistently related in healthy children: A systematic review and meta-analysis. *Sleep Medicine Reviews*, *51*, 101278. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.smrv.2020.101278 | Citations: 20; JIF: 11.6; CNCI: 1.2

Sanders, T., Parker, P. D., del Pozo-Cruz, B., Noetel, M., & Lonsdale, C. (2019). Type of screen time moderates effects on outcomes in 4013 children: Evidence from the Longitudinal Study of Australian Children. *International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity*, 16(1), 117. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12966-019-0881-7 | Citations: 49; JIF: 6.7; CNCI: 3.9

Sanders, T., Feng, X., Fahey, P. P., Lonsdale, C., & Astell-Burt, T. (2015). The influence of neighbourhood green space on children's physical activity and screen time: Findings from the longitudinal study of Australian children. *International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity*, 12(1), 126. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12966-015-0288-z| Citations: 56; JIF: 4; CNCI: 2.5

BOOK CHAPTERS

Parker, P., Guo, J., & **Sanders, T.** (2019). Socioeconomic Inequality and Student Outcomes in Australia. In L. Volante, S. V. Schnepf, J. Jerrim, & D. A. Klinger (Eds.), *Socioeconomic Inequality and Student Outcomes: Cross-National Trends, Policies, and Practices* (pp. 189–204). Springer Singapore. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-13-9863-6_11

Research Funding

Australian Research Council	\$658,544
CHIEF INVESTIGATOR — DISCOVERY PROJECT DP200101912	2020-2023
SQUARE EYES OR ALL LIES? UNDERSTANDING CHILDREN'S EXPOSURE TO SCREENS.	2020 2020
Australian Catholic University	\$21,597
CHIEF INVESTIGATOR (LEAD) — TRANSLATE4IMPACT	
RAISING AWARENESS OF THE RISKS AND BENEFITS OF CHILDREN'S INTERACTIONS WITH ELECTRONIC SCREENS TO PARENTS	2023-2023
AND POLICYMAKERS	
Catholic Schools New South Wales	\$76,333
CHIEF INVESTIGATOR	2021–2022
AUSTRALIAN PRINCIPAL HEALTH AND WELLBEING	2021-2022
NSW Department of Education	\$20,000
CHIEF INVESTIGATOR	2019–2020
IPLAY FOR INCLUSION	2013-2020
Sport Australia	\$248,802
Chief Investigator — 'Move It Aus' Participation Grant Program	2019–2020
IPLAY FOR INCLUSION	2013 2020
Australian Sports Commission	\$54,546
CHIEF INVESTIGATOR	2019–2019
IPLAY Sporting Schools Pilot Project	2013 2013
Australian Catholic University	\$7,865
CHIEF INVESTIGATOR (LEAD) — FACULTY OF HEALTH SCIENCES RESEARCH PROJECT GRANT SCHEME	2018–2018
INVESTIGATING THE CORRELATES OF CHILDREN'S SCREEN TIME	2010-2010
NSW Department of Education	\$11,500
CHIEF INVESTIGATOR	2018–2018
IPLAY NUTRITION PROOF-OF-CONCEPT MODULE	2018-2018

Awards_____

- 2013 **Australian Postgraduate Award** Western Sydney University. \$105,000AUD plus tuition fees.
- 2017 **ACU Discipline Winner and National Finalist** 5 Minute Research Pitch.
- 2021 **Excellence and Innovation in Public Health Education and Research** Council of Academic Public Health Institutions Australasia. Team Award (iPLAY Project)
- Vice-Chancellor's Staff Excellence Award: Excellence in Research and Research Partnership Australian Catholic University. Team Award (iPLAY Project)
- Vice-Chancellor's Staff Excellence Award: Excellence in Research and Research Partnership Australian Catholic University. Team Award (Principals Project)

Students_

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY

2016–2020 Jane Lee	Assistant Supervisor
2016–2021 Devan Antcazk	Assistant Supervisor
2019–2022 Katrina Wilhite	Principal Supervisor
2020– Bridget Booker	Principal Supervisor
2020– Roberta Vasconcellos	Co-supervisor
2021– Ella Tremaine	Principal Supervisor
2022– Anum Urooj	Principal Supervisor

Honours

2019–2019 Bridget Booker Principal Supervisor

Invited Talks_____

Australian Council for Health, Physical Education and Recreation. Keynote Lecture: Evidence-Based

School Physical Activity Programs. K-6 Physical Activity and Health Conference

2021 **ResBaz Sydney**. Keystory: How We Do Reproducible Research.

Conference Presentations

2018

(Presenting author presentations listed only)

Lonsdale, C., Lubans, D., Noetel, M., & **Sanders, T.** (2019). Scaling-up an Efficacious Comprehensive School-based Physical Activity Intervention: Development, Evaluation and Dissemination of the iPLAY Program. *Sports Medicine Australia*.

Sanders, T., Parker, P. D., Del Pozo-Cruz, B., Noetel, M., & Lonsdale, C. (2019). Content of Screen Time Moderates the Effects of Exposure on Physical Health, Psychological and Educational Outcomes in a Longitudinal Study of 4,013 Children. *International Society for Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity*.

Sanders, T., Lonsdale, C., & Del Pozo-Cruz, B. (2018). Sleep Quality Mediates the Relationship between Screen Time and Depression in Adults: A Cross-Sectional Study of the NHANES 2005-2006 Cycle. *International Society for Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity*.

Sanders, T., Feng, X., Fahey, P. P., Lonsdale, C., & Astell-Burt, T. (2017). Neighbourhood Green Space and Children's Enjoyment of Physical Activity: Evidence from the Longitudinal Study of Australian Children. *SELF Conference*.

Sanders, T., Feng, X., Fahey, P. P., Lonsdale, C., & Astell-Burt, T. (2016). Does Physical Activity Explain the Relationship Between Green Space and Children's BMI? Mediation Analyses from the Longitudinal Study of Australian Children. *International Society for Physical Activity and Health*.

Sanders, T., Feng, X., Fahey, P. P., Lonsdale, C., & Astell-Burt, T. (2015). The Longitudinal Influence of Neighbourhood Green Space on Children's Physical Activity, Screen Time, and Body Mass Index. *International Society for Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity*.

Selected Software

For a complete list of the software I have developed or contributed to, please see my Github page.

R PACKAGES

cloudstoR CRAN Link

Provides programmatic access to AARNET's CloudStor cloud storage service

- Author and Maintainer.
- Available on CRAN approx 400 downloads per month.

sleepIPD GitHub Link

A STANDARDISED METHOD FOR REPROCESSING ACCELEROMETERY DATA FOR A VERY LARGE SLEEP AND PHYSICAL ACTIVITY

POOLED ANALYSIS

- · Author and Maintainer.
- Used by teams all over the world to reprocess data exactly as required for our study.

gt3x2csv GitHub Link

CONVERT ACTIGRAPH GT3X FILES TO CSV, IN A FRACTION OF THE TIME

- Author and Maintainer.
- Approximately 7x faster than using the proprietary software.

PYTHON PACKAGES

faceblurring GitHub Link

An implementation of a face detection model used to protect privacy in an ARC project

- Author and Maintainer.
- · Working version available, still in development.

JUNE 2023 TAREN SANDERS · CURRICULUM VITAE